all right thank you everyone today is
February 5th 2024 and Oli will be
facilitating this discussion on chapter
one for cohort 6 so thanks
Oli okay uh hello everyone thanks for
joining for our first discussion for
chapter one uh well um as you might have
read in in the content and uh also for
the introduction in chapter one uh this
is sorry this chapter gives a kind of um
overall picture of uh what kind of
theory active inference is uh and
specifically uh what kind of approach uh
the textbook is going to take explaining
different aspects of um active inference
Theory uh well one of the main themes of
uh this chapter and U also the overall
organizational scheme of the textbook is
uh the difference
between two kind of approach to active
inference literature namely uh the high
road and the low road so basically uh
for high road uh the prior assumption is
the existence of quote unquote things
and then explaining from that um
seemingly obvious assumption into what
uh what requirements that quote unquote
thing uh should have in order for it to
have U many various uh aspects such as
agency uh as a kind of decision maker
and so on so basically uh it's not
something specific to cognitive agents
but uh the whole framework can also be
applied to many other uh uh many other
agents uh as long as it can be described
in terms of its internal and external
Dynamics so uh that's one approach to
active inference the other one uh which
uh is usually called Low Road in the
literature is beginning from uh some of
the concepts developed uh from back in
the 19th century uh for example by
people such as Helm holes uh in which
they kind of they it tries to
generalize uh the basian reasoning uh
into um
unto un developing uh the notion of free
energy and specifically variation free
energy uh for which we can um we can
formulate
uh the way that that the organisms or
agents can perceive the world and also
uh the related variable or related
so-called parameter uh so for uh for
perception we need a kind of lower
boundary which is the AAL free energy
and uh for um for control or for
decision making uh we need uh another uh
variable or parameter namely expected
free energy so by describing these two
parameters as kind of lower bound of
certainty we can uh again formulate how
uh organisms or cognitive agents can
engage in both perception and also
action so basically when we say active
inference it's uh it implies a kind of
integration of these two um these two
aspects of perception and action so
they're not uh essentially distinct from
each other uh both of them uh both of
them kind of um follow a similar
trajectory or similar mathem iCal uh
technology but uh in somewhat mirror or
uh reversed way so um I hope I uh I
could give a kind of overall meaning of
what high road and low road uh mean but
obviously we'll uh we'll get to see much
more detail of both of these approaches
so the uh the chapter two deals with um
the introdu uction of low road approach
and then beginning from chapter 3 we'll
see how high road approach differs from
uh the low road one so um if anyone has
any thought or comments or question on
these two concepts or we can go to the
question section and
see uh and discuss some of the questions
positive
there
okay so maybe we can open the question
section
or by the way
yeah no on that question um so in the in
the chapter it talks about the fact that
organisms or just agents can not the
motivation is to reduce surprise but
they may not able to act on surprise
directly but instead on what's called
proxies could you and they see that's a
variation the free end variation free
energy could you clarify what we mean by
that or just giv some examples of that
sure so yeah the concept of surprise uh
actually is a little bit different than
uh the psychological conception of
surprise uh that we're familiar with in
everyday parlament but uh basically what
we mean inactive inference by surprise
is its uh statistic in its a statistical
sense so uh it's surprisal as a
functional uh and uh yes so variational
free energy is a kind of upper bound of
this function or this surprisal this
parameter uh in which uh so the the
agent um when it engages in the act
perception it tries to minimize this
upper bound or at least uh to somehow
optimize its error uh so that the uh KL
Divergence of its error wouldn't exceed
this uh bound to this variational free
energy so basically uh
by specifying this uh oper bound or or
this bound as an optimization parameter
uh we can deal with approximate basian
inference instead of exact basian
inference so we don't need to exactly or
precisely specify uh the Divergence of
uh the perception from uh the input data
uh instead we can specify a kind of uh
bound to to
approximately uh minimize that error in
order uh for the perception to have some
meaningful um to have any kind of
meaning uh for us uh in terms of its
action or any uh subsequent um
subsequent message passing and so on uh
so yes here uh variation free energy
again is a paramet is an optim
optimization parameter
uh so uh the agent in active inference
framework uh will try to somehow
minimize this uh or actually optimize uh
this
parameter based on the Divergence more
specifically the KL callback lier
Divergence between the input data and
its uh generative
model we'll see how it works uh more
precisely and More rigorously in chapter
two but uh free energy yes is the
surprisal or the parameter uh the agent
tries to
minimize and variational free energy is
kind of a get around uh so that instead
of engaging in uh exact basian inference
we just need to do the approximate
basian inference which is much more
tractable
than the exact basian inference because
as we know basian inference uh for U
anything more than very very simple
cases are extremely
intractable I had a a quick question
about that if that's okay yes sure um
and by the way it's okay if we need to
put a pin in this and um and perhaps
address it in a later chapter as well I
am I am interested in um not being super
familiar with um with the that
intractability problem do you know what
it is that makes that straight up basian
computation in intractable and and how
does uh variational free energy get
around that or should we save that for
later
time okay so a preliminary answer would
be uh so in order to do um an exact
basian inference we need to account for
every single parameter every single
variable that uh that is relevant uh for
U any kind of real real world situation
uh so as we know uh when when we want
when we want to uh want to model any any
kind of real world situation uh
basically the sheer number of variables
we need to account uh are is extremely
uh I
mean uh say for some very very simple
cases in other cases we need to account
for many many more variables so it makes
uh the situation much more complicated
uh so um and also we might not also know
uh the exact Val for every parameter or
even what parameters to account for
right uh but uh when we want uh when uh
as a way to get around this uh problem
uh we might want to engage in a
proximate basian inference in which uh
instead of uh Computing the exact value
of a prior we approximate it by doing a
kind of margin
alization on uh the variables we know
the value of it of them and so it kind
of gives uh much more um realistic way
uh to compute those um those posteriors
posteriors uh in any kind of situation
so uh that's a much more tractable
situation than U or basically we can say
that Computing exact basian inference uh
in uh most situations can be seen not
only intractable but almost
impossible um as I said we might not
know the exact value of the parameters
we want to model so uh yes that's uh one
of
the um essential
issues uh of doing any kind of basing
statistics basian inference and um
almost always uh the the number here in
the parameter in the denominator py is
almost always marginalized in um real
work
situations so that marginalization over
py uh instead of the exact value of
py um is basically called approximate
basian
imprints fantastic it was very clear
thank you just to add like one more
point there because it's a great
question so like in the setting of
basian phog gentics X the hidden state
was the real relationship among species
unobserved and then Y is a huge data set
so it might be millions of lines or
something like that um the likelihood of
that data set being observed like Ali
said like if you knew that you'd kind of
have already known so not only is it a
massive data set but but it this
question seems to require you to know
what you already want to know and then
um the variational inference which is a
computational heris approach that's
existed long before active inference
like variational autoencoders and the
technique here is kind of like reducing
to a certain family of models that only
have a few knobs to fiddle with like I'm
going to fiddle with the mean and the
variance of this distribution and that's
it and then there are smoothly
incrementally optimizable paths for this
sorry for this kind of a problem that
you can take in time incrementally
versus this which is just like a massive
static problem that is intractable for
sometimes a number of reasons and so the
approach taken to the action perception
Loop in active inference just to a first
pass is to treat it like this kind of
structure fixed though you know asterisk
later developments but just at the core
level is to treat it like a structurally
fixed optimization
problem rather than this sort of static
number
crunch much appreciated thank
you um and also as a side note um
there's this fascinating pre-print uh
which was I think released um a couple
of weeks ago namely naturalizing
relevance realization so the concept of
relevance realization uh by John Veri is
uh very relevant here so
uh basically what they claim in that
paper is uh cognition is
fundamentally uh uncomputable in its in
uh very well- defined algorithmic sense
but uh predictive processing
uh via using a
probabilistic uh modeling instead of uh
using the exact values for parameters uh
they can actually provide a much more
realistic way uh to in order to model uh
the information processing nature of uh
any kind of uh biological organisms uh
obviously including the brains so I
highly recommend reading uh this paper
to I think yeah it is this one so yeah
so basically relevance
realization so what John Veri means by
relevance uh is exactly uh the
parameters we need to uh model or we
need to account for in order to
meaningfully model the behavior of the
organism uh which is
huge okay so any other comments
questions
or we can look at some of the
questions and the coda
page
all right so
uh uh we may dwell a little bit on the
distinction between the low road and
high road and as career uh opinions uh I
mean before reading uh the book for uh
those of you uh uh who are approaching
this book for the first time uh what do
you think uh the
advantages or disadvantages of using um
each of these approaches uh to active
influence literature based on uh this uh
preliminary understanding of the
distinction between these two
approaches or which one would you find
more meaningful I don't know more
logical and so
on I I would say um I was struck by the
way that um the high road provides this
sort of like um great overview you know
like a very elegant explanation that
just begins with this simple fundamental
predicament of self-organizing
systems um so I find it very useful
conceptually in that sense I was
explaining trying to explain active
inference to someone who's not familiar
with it recently and uh I was kind of
talking about some of these Concepts and
he said uh yeah but that's you're you're
using mentalizing Concepts right um and
uh the a agentic
perspective um that's introduced by the
high road model I think is interesting
and and I'd like to um learn more about
how this relates to this sort of um
ontology like what the ontology behind
it is because it seems to really um go
against a lot of the sort of um
you know the approach uh the sort of
deterministic
um uh you know traditional approach
where there's this gap between kind of
agents and Consciousness and mentalizing
Concepts and then a world that's purely
determined like is there formal
causation because creatures have evolved
you know um that's a little mysterious
to me so that's that's what struck
me great thanks uh yeah uh that's a
great point I mean uh one of actually as
far as I know one of the main discussion
points of whole active inference
literature is exactly uh focused on uh
kind of unentangled uh what kind of
metaphors they use and uh making them
more uh precise uh so um I agree that
some of some of the metaphors used in
active inference can seem at first uh
kind of I don't know uh appealing to a
kind of panych
psychism kind of kind of approach or um
I don't know make them uh a bit uh more
anth
anthropocentric than it than it really
is uh but um it's important to
keep uh this point in mind that uh some
of the terms used in active inference
are used in their U very technical and
uh mathematically rigorous sense so for
instance uh there was a debate around
the use of the word sentience uh in one
of the papers which published u a few
months
ago so uh the way active inference
literature uses this word sentence is
actually uh specifically and rigorously
defined in some of the papers uh and
it's not necessarily something that
perfectly maps onto the everyday
conception of of this word or even uh in
the sense of sense of the this word
that's used in some other relevant
disciplines or other related areas uh
but yes that's a great point and uh by
the way
uh I almost forgot it um I usually refer
to this great paper or rather essay by
Carl priston namely beyond the desert
landscape uh from uh the book Andy Clark
and his critics in which uh he
beautifully uh explains uh the
difference between low road and high
road and why active inference literature
relies more recently on developing the
high road approach instead of the low
road one so I highly recommend reading
uh that essay as well
Thomas yeah I mean kind of piggy back on
that question on the high road I had a
lot of interest in that I don't have
experience knowing about Marco blankets
I think that seems very clearly one of
the major definitions of what we're
getting at there so I can't make a
comment about that yet I imagine we're
going to talk about that in future
chapters when I was reading that I
reminded from Plato's Mino there there's
discourse about the definition of figure
and it's using a very particular mode of
discussion about to talk about defining
what color coming as a followup of
figure so and it's a discussion of limit
uh in fact even play's character has a
very particular kind of nuance
discussion that that can even challenge
the discussion what limit is so that's
is more just meditating on I think
that's very I'm interested in hearing
more about that um at this
point yeah we'll definitely come to uh
markup blank get in chapter three and uh
hopefully we'll have an extensive
discussion around that uh essential
concept and I agree markup blanket um I
mean holds Central um central place in
all active inference literature so
uh thanks Daniel
Jeff yeah I'm just I'm just reminded uh
not from the last bit of conversation
but just a little bit before that and
I'm sorry I'm jumping in in the middle
here uh but I'm just reminded of
wheeler's partici for a Universe
[Music]
um wheeler
participant okay so uh interesting uh
you see uh I'm not uh very familiar with
Wheeler's work but um as far as I know
uh I mean some of the ideas from um I
mean uh some of Wheeler's ideas and
specifically uh
the uh bestowing a kind of
fundamentality to the concept of
information uh which is one of the um
wheelers as far as I know um main
arguments uh so uh
is very very similar to what basian
mechanics um way of modeling uh the
physics and and I don't mean just physic
of belief but actually physics of
everything so I'm not sure if you've
heard
B basian mechanics but it's a kind of
new way of uh doing uh even fundamental
physics not only uh as a way to model
cognitive agents uh but U it is much
more fundamental than that uh so uh as
the work the works of people like um
Delton activ Adel would show uh this new
kind of approach to doing uh physics
is uh in some sense perfectly congruent
with everything uh that has come so far
in in the history of fundamental physics
in terms of its classical I mean
classical physics quantum physics and
even for modeling uh dynamical chaotic
systems so
uh yes um the uh the notion of uh
fundamentality of information or rather
the fundamentality of beliefs belief in
its statistical sense uh which is a kind
of uh a mod modulated information is a
kind of uh is a kind of information that
has a specific probability
distribution uh is Central to um I mean
uh almost everything active inference
related or Fe related so yes I think uh
they're closely related to Wheeler's
work as well and also obviously Chris
Fields a great course on in physics as
information processing
uh has some great discussions around
that point as
well I'm editing the journal right
now yeah Jeff that will be awesome to
see some connections with Chris fields
and and to make a comment on this I
think cognitive science in a way is
looking for that kind of
qualified description of things in their
environment figure and ground and agent
in environment ecological
psychology and
um there are various like
seemingly uh overly simplistic to the
point of losing their epistemic or
pragmatic value theories like um
theories that might be criticized as um
like for example even in this discussion
words that have been brought up like
mentalizing or
anthropocentric so clearly those could
be taken to a level where it's like yeah
it we you know out mentalized where it's
not even useful and it's anthropocentric
where it doesn't even apply to this or
that um or the other way around and then
also anything that's part of our
behavior and experience it is coming in
some way through the apparatus of the
person so it can only be escaped so
fundamentally and so sometimes there's a
movement away from so-called
anthropocentrism but then it's like if
it doesn't have us doing that theory
then what is that really even trying to
describe
then David
yeah hi good morning yes I just wanted
to uh see if uh the mous Utopia studies
would fall into this dynamic as well uh
performed by John Calhoun in the 60s I'm
not sure if you're familiar with the
studies
themselves in terms of uh the behavioral
modeling um because they do describe it
as a collapse in behavior and in terms
of a
predetermined you know Utopia from a
different
experiential point of view and then
seeing how that deteriorated despite the
constraints on the model itself um
wanted to know how that might speak
towards uh you know the behavioral
modeling itself and uh the collapse
function how that might be related to
the basium mechanics as well in terms of
uh defining an environmental space you
know for another U active group of
agents for
example thanks David I'm not familiar
with this work at all so thanks for
bringing
it up and introducing it um I don't know
if anyone is familiar with mous Utopia
experiments and
uh yeah Jeff go for
it no I I that that leads directly into
I think um Mar OB Blake and in the
holographic principle um and and um
layers of separation between agents and
the translation that has to occur at
every hop right right um for example
we're not going to be able to empathize
with what it's like to be a bacteria in
a bacterial Colony but for the
bacteria they take a very bacterio
Centric view of the world so I think
it's very natural for us and it's right
for us to take a anthropocentric uh
approach right because that's our lived
experience and I think there's definite
overlap with with with with psychology
and soci the social sciences in general
there right um we can't imagine what
it's like to be a sun but if you look at
tile hard's complexity Theory right like
anything with sufficient complexity has
Consciousness so you know the sun knows
what it's like to be a sun the Sun but
but but you know it's building that it's
building that translators and the steps
between the different systems is is
really what what I'm interested in
getting after right so it's kind of like
the rock being able to imagine it's a
rock but not interact with another rock
for example yeah yeah yeah exactly
yeah I just found it interesting because
the uh the mouse St itself where they
they teered the different areas and then
they kind of segregated it so you know
they had you know different levels but
you know that's also coming from my
background which is sociology so I mean
there's a little bit of Prior from
myself there as well
so so I'd also have to learn more about
the experiment specifically but I think
one phenomena it speaks to is the
unified nature of cognitive phenomena
in the developmental in The evolutionary
setting like you could study just
working memory and you go down the
rabbit hole and then working memory is
going to bleed off into some other
cognitive phenomena because it's all
happening in part of this integrated
unit of of organismal function and then
when we take that view out to like the
intergenerational and the social so
they're like vertical and horizontal
transmission all these different kinds
of inheritance mechanisms then
oh let's just invent a pencil to offload
this and then there's nonlinear effects
or let's just make this well make this
thing that was clear now let's paint
over that like changes to what what can
um influence one cognitive phenomena or
one kind of intervention or change in
the game can lead to like these
cascading effects all these different
kinds of ecological
Dynamics so that kind of motivates that
kind of motivates at least the
integrated framework to prepare for the
um proper analysis of these complex
situations
yeah do you think those decision non
sself motivated in that sense you know
where um you know something that's
single cellular might you know has two
fella for example it's going to drop one
um because it may not you know be able
to exist with two in that in that you
know environment itself but is that
necessarily a choice or is that a
product of the environment
itself and also uh I mean the whole
verging field of Basil cognition also
deals uh with these kinds of questions I
mean whether uh those single celled
organisms uh actually possess kind of uh
primitive U cognition uh in terms of
memory learning decision making and so
on and uh how it how it's implemented
biologically so uh one uh strong
candidate for um for the way I mean for
uh the
implementation of uh the basil cognition
in uh any uh even the single cell
organisms uh is through the uh Gap
Junction distribution of their of their
bioelectric network uh which is the main
uh research one of the
main areas of research um people such as
Michael Levan and his colleagues uh so
yeah it's a very interesting um
developments in recent uh biology uh
so the whole are of Basil cognition as
far as I know uh officially started from
2021 so they're very new questions and
uh obviously with the mainstream uh
biology concerned uh concerned on uh uh
the modern synthesis uh approach uh it's
a long way uh to somehow nudge uh nudge
the Paradigm and uh to make a through
true paradigm shift in biology but uh
it's happening and uh I I believe uh
they can lead to uh some really exciting
uh new work in this area once uh we
escape uh the traditional uh Gene
centered uh view of the organisms uh to
the the more holistic and organism
centered um ontology so that can that
can also apply
to uh even non-biological agents if we
want to uh think of the Continuum
between uh biological things and
non-biological ones as a true Continuum
not not not uh something that
uh that something that has any kind of
um
fundamental uh difference between
between them so basian mechanics uh is
one of the approaches that somehow
dismantles uh this um discrepan this
fundamental discrepancy between uh
biological and
non-biological agents uh so yeah I
believe uh it's a much more interesting
worldview to look at things this way in
a kind of Continuum as a kind of process
and so on instead of uh aristan
essentialism that's great I'll just add
one more thing I don't want to give too
much input but you jogged my memory on
something related to something I was
thinking about with uh Len's work as
well in terms of you know if you have a
more macro level like a human being for
example and you have uh you know an
accident or something and a limb needs
to be removed we have this you know
Phantom limb we call it where the
individual still feels like they can
move the limb the limb might still be
there but you know it has been removed
so obviously there is some memory there
but we also know that we have neurons
you know and extremities in our bodies
you know to what extent is that you know
a mechanic of just cognition or is it
also a mechanic of the potential energy
that was lost in that space for example
and would we be able to pinpoint that
kind of thing with the technology we
have now to try and rep replicate that
on a smaller scale to kind of find that
you
know bioelectric signal or whatever else
might be going on in terms of you know
the interconnectivity between the micro
and the macro and that
Dynamic thank you great uh okay Cohen I
noticed you had your hand raised if I'm
not mistaken you want to add anything or
or
ywn if I had my hand raised that was a
mistake sorry but I I yesterday I
listened to the fron and and Levin talk
and uh it it seemed super interesting to
me that Levin thinks
that like
he has simulated some systems where like
some genotypes understand that other
agents share it the genotype and uh they
Fair much better and they like
communicate much better with agents that
are very similar
themselves yeah
interesting uh actually we'll have a lot
more to talk about uh all of these
things in the coming chapters and uh as
I said it's uh one of the uh main
focuses of uh active inference uh
especially uh from its high level
approach so um I'm excited to hear all
the I mean your opinions on all of these
matters uh as we
come uh to those points as well
so Jeff uh did you want to add anything
or yeah um I my background is National
Security military and uh intelligence
community and working overseas like for
for the US Military and um there's a
massive problem right now with security
classification and also with also
Enterprise it and cyber security um
massive problem with with um information
classification controlling classified
information and
um zero trust and protecting information
on the internet right the internet is a
scale-free system uh so I think there's
a practical applicability here to
fundamentally redesigning the way that
we look at protecting our information on
the internet and this really could be a
practicum and I've got about 6,000 words
uh in a paper if anybody's interested in
collaborating uh short deadline uh I'm
targeting it for a conference called the
hammeron which is um one of the big
National Security conferences in the
country it's right outside the NSA
headquarters and um yeah so I'm I'm I'm
actively working on that um and I I
think it's a very very um like re like
Salient point and And Timely Point um to
our current
conversation very
interesting thanks for bringing it up if
anyone is interested in
collaboration
uh that would be exciting and
great okay so quick question sorry aliot
what would be the best way through this
group uh to be in touch about things
like that in the future I'm not sure Jee
if if uh my background would be would be
especially helpful on that but I'm just
curious about like what's the the sort
of best practice on how to link up for
that kind of thing if
so I'll just answer it um on the cooh
six page you can add like a row with
your contact
info you could also message someone in
Zoom if you're synchronously here or
just find any other way another option
is to write on the
projects
page and that can include your contact
information so if you want to kind of
check out other people's projects or
plant your own um here if you want to
kind of just do it more personally at
the this page also understanding that
everything that's in the textbook group
document is like open essentially and
just contact each other and enjoy beyond
the halls of The
Institute awesome
thanks I'm like Curious just any anyone
else um even if they haven't added
anything like just how is chapter
[Music]
one how did they feel like it opened the
book or what did it leave them
with yes
Petra yeah uh hi I have a question about
uh uh normative framework
um I'm just thinking is it like uh the
framework describes uh healthy
functioning organism when we are looking
at a human uh as a as a agent
or uh is it meant uh differently I'm
thinking um in a context of uh
Psychopathology when we are talking that
the uh agents model generative model is
somehow sub optimized uh whether it is
connected with this uh normative uh
aspect of framework does it make sense
sorry great question great question
thank you uh so um I'll take a first
step so uh uh you see uh the use of this
word normative here u in active
inference literature and also in the
textbook is uh somewhat uh I think
defined in the notes if I'm yes it was
in page U on page
267 so here it says the term normative
means uh there is some evaluative
standard against which behavior can be
scored active inference is normative in
the sense that perception and action are
scored by free energy a quantity we will
unpack throughout this and the next
chapters so as I said again uh it's more
technical uh sense of the word normative
and it's not necessarily congruent with
um other um connotations or meanings of
this word so uh basically uh the reason
uh it's I mean the word normative used
uh in active inference is to refer to uh
this Central parameter namely free
energy as the main optimization
parameter uh around which all the other
formulation and um I mean mathematical
formalism revolves so uh that's
basically uh as far as I understand uh
the meaning of the word the adjective
normative in active inference literature
but I'd be happy to hear any other
opinion uh on that matter as
well thanks Ali thank you Petra um I'll
just add a few other points especially
in the social and human there was some
great discussion on this question of
normativity in the social sciences
course with ma alasen um and Ben White
and others and AVL last year um so
especially in the and um it it it is um
an interesting question and one that
also people have specifically looked at
in the um Psychopathology sense like
Carl friston and Thomas par two of the
three authors on the textbook are
clinicians and so there's a lot of
discussion about like well what does it
mean if it's Bas optimal but it's DSM
diagnosed like how how is it what is it
that's going right or wrong what's
optimal or
nonoptimal and just different ways to
talk about like what is optimal like
under this um memory parameter this
Behavior can be understood as optimal
and so that's a kind of like narrow Bas
optimal but then that's just what
prepares for the discussion like but
then the context
this is not aligning with their
preferences
so it's a great question though and and
also like um just the is and the art and
oh well active inference can be applied
to um this system you know we know it
can be applied to any system oh can be
applied to a company so it ought to be
this way but a framework that just
describes how things are how do you go
from that to how it ought to
be and also again as a side note uh I
will refer to Mark bier's work as well
because uh much of his research uh is um
is concentrated on uh again the
development of what it actually means uh
for U for an organism or an agent to
have a normative perception or normative
action and uh what it what it means U is
a kind of gold Direct edness action or
kind of intentional intentional action
or as what Terence Deacon would call
intentional not necessarily intentional
uh so um this kind of normative uh
perception or normative action as uh
bicker develops in U many of his papers
U is the sense that uh this kind of
intentionality is uh unseparable from
the perception and obviously the action
but um
in in the so-called um tiop phobic uh
community of biologists uh this this
kind of discourse uh somehow sometimes
would uh raise eyebrows because uh as we
know uh from I don't know around U 1950
on word uh there's this kind of phobia
around this Theology and any kind of uh
I mean go directedness and U to put
intentionality uh and mechanistic
explanations and so on but uh as Terence
ston also shows an incomplete nature um
uh and as I said Mark bier's work um
this intentionality and
normativity uh are essential aspects of
uh any sentient and cognitive agent uh
and by uh agent I mean anything from
single cell organism to uh I don't know
much more complex on so
um uh thanks for your question yeah oh
yeah think great points Allan to kind of
connect the like what you described
earlier about the Theology and TI tiop
phobia and the Deacon and the absenti
nature the idea that there are systems
um for whom deterministic accounting of
their connections accounts for their
behavior like a a pendulum or something
like that but even a system um like a
pendulum could be described as like this
absenti movement towards and so there
are fundamental parts of especially
symbolic knowledge based systems that
have um a teely logical cause like the
cause of the house is that there was a
desire to build a house in that place um
and
so active inference especially in this
chapter one setting it just like brings
it all out on the table the chapter does
and and the discussions do and um
there's a lot in the chapter and also a
lot that's kind of like a adjacency
that's always fun to bring out and this
is kind of just like calibrating to the
scope of the kinds of things that that
are our starting point for continuing
with the journey and just seeing about
like some of the heris stics and tools
and frames that have been brought um up
previously and then in this first half
of the textbook we kind of like get
through one worked example with the
mamalian nervous system by chapter five
of like this is kind of of the sketch of
what it looks like to start applying
this to a system but here's how much
work it takes to get to this stage and
here's what the model does and doesn't
say at that
stage thanks
Daniel okay so at our final minutes um
I'd be interested to hear uh now that
you've read chapter one uh what do you
anticipate uh or what do you hope uh to
gain from Reading um the textbook all
the way
through I mean does reading chapter one
change your
anticipation for better or worse
or
yes
as
yeah I think
Thomas raised his
hand oh uh sorry I have some problems
seeing the race okay Thomas thanks oh
sure um no it hasn't this chapter didn't
really change my anticipations mainly
because Daniel was so generous when I
talked with him in the Discord chat he
sent me that paper on order and change
in this art basically how to give the
active inference account could apply to
aesthetic experience phenomenal I mean
my research and writings for Plato's
account of Aesthetics like lines up
perfectly to what that paper was talking
about and if anything I'm just more in
I'm excited to move forward I think the
idea that we I think the account really
interesting um I think the fact that
priston does a great job making an
argument that aesthetic experience is
not being suppressed are kind of De
decomposed down um basically on the
account of epistemic arcs I think that's
outstanding um as an account for the
aesthetic
experience and I think the fact that
this can be rigorously discussed is
that's the area why I'm even here in the
first place because I TR I for anyone
doesn't remember call it see meaning me
I'm a lecturer in visual art at a
university and the biggest challenge I
have with pupil students is to
rigorously demonstrate how do we know
something's more successful or not so
this kind of normative measure measure
kind of approach um the fact that that
can be demonstrated in such rigorous
ways I'm very interested um but also the
mystery of basically hyra has a whole
paper on the question of what's the
thing this whole question of That's So
the kind of high road even question of
how to answer what is a thing uh is just
I'm very fascinated nothing's really
been changed I'm more just I'm enjoying
the meal I'm looking forward to the next
course that be my summary so
far thanks uh and on the point of
Aesthetics uh actually there's this
recent um exciting uh special issue um
and I think it was in um philosophical
transactions of Royal Society on the
subject of Aesthetics from the Viewpoint
of predictive
processing uh which
um okay yes Al exactly it was in this
issue also tomorrow um with uh Karen
Konan the guest stream um about
literature and predictive processing
that should be super exciting too I'll
put this in the notes
yeah she uses um the predictive
processing uh as
applied she applies predictive
processing uh to uh literary studies and
uh somehow uses literature as a kind of
experimental hub for investigating many
facets of Consciousness from the
Viewpoint of predictive processing it's
really fascinating
work awesome cool all right well thank
you Ali for the facilitation and thank
you everyone um next week we'll continue
to discuss chapter one in the later time
period or feel free to comment this time
again and we'll be um talking about
chapter 6 the recipe for generative
modeling so thank you all farewell
thanks for joining everyone bye
bye